[Music]
hello and welcome everyone it is january
2022.
we are here in actin flab live stream
number 35.2
discussing the paper a tale of two
architectures free energy its models and
modularity
welcome to the actin flap we are an
online participatory lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find
more information on this slide
this is a recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve our work
if you're watching live feel free to
write questions in the live chat if
you're watching in replay you can also
add comments
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here and we'll be following good
video etiquette for live streams
all of our activities in the lab are
participatory so if you would like to
contribute or get involved go to
activeinference.org
and see what is there
today in
live stream 35.2 we're going to be
having our third discussion continuing
on the paper a tale of two architectures
free energy its models and modularity
written by majeed benny who we're really
appreciative is joining us today to talk
and see where it goes so we'll um get to
the introduction in a second but
basically we're gonna just
pick up on some of the threads that we
opened in earlier discussions we have a
few specific things written down
and
i'm sure we'll go many different ways
with people joining and ideas coming up
and
questions in a live chat and all of that
so we can kind of go any which way but
we'll just start with the introduction
and warm up so we can each say hello
maybe blue and i can just say what we're
excited about for the dot two and then
mageed it'd be awesome to hear any
context for the paper so i'm daniel i'm
a researcher in california
and
i
didn't expect the rabbit duck to appear
in dot one
but i'm looking forward to continuing
that and seeing how is this drawing like
a scientific model
and then what does that
philosophical or conceptual paradox or
ambiguity say about scientific modeling
so blue
i'm blue i'm a researcher in new mexico
and i am excited to
probe deeper into the relationship um
between agents and their environment and
also the intransitivity um argument and
modularity and how those kind of all fit
together
excellent ajit
you are muted and then please continue
so hello you can hear me no
so uh i'm magic i'm an assistant
professor of philosophy at metoo middle
east technical university and
i'm obsessed with
models and structures across science and
perception and mind and
this is for it's for a while that i'm
engaged with this issue of model
applying model-based approach to
science to free energy principle and
predictive coding and i'm very happy to
be here thank you very much for inviting
me
great well maybe just for like
background and context
what
brought you to write this
specific paper like recognizing
modularity as an important topic and
where does this fit into
some of your other
threads related to fep and model based
science
um
well well
that's a very good question i'm not uh
quite sure why
so one reason for
uh
focusing on modularity in this paper is
that uh most probably it has some sort
of psychological explanation because i
started to learn about philosophy of
mine and philosophy of collective
science by
reading this language of toads and
i think that even in the earlier stages
when i was when people were studying
there no one was thinking that the brain
is actually a syntactical engine
no one was thinking that
if you open up a brain or a cognitive
system you actually find things that are
inside the brain in terms of
uh propositional like entities language
like entities or syntactical engines or
anything of that sort but
at the same time people were believing
that that perspective on hold brain
works
uh have some sort of explanatory gain
there is something that we can learn by
taking that perspective on
uh the brain and cognitive system
and
well i think that uh
the
general idea behind beyond behind
applying this model-based approach to
sciences is that it is the explanatory
interest explanatory as well as
practical interests of the modeler of
the people who are engaged with
scientific enterprise that
uh provide a handle on
the target system the things that we try
to explore and understand and uh
well uh i think that then i was reading
uh
uh the target paper uh by uh by
kirchoff and hippolytu uh
well uh
what
what stroked me as odd was that uh
they were taking it very very much for
granted true of course through very well
articulated
and philosophical arguments that
[Music]
there is no
such modularity inside the brain or
cognitive system
and i just wanted to bring the point to
attention that it would be a matter of
as i said earlier practical and
explanatory goals and interests of the
modeler whether there is
a modularity there or not so
uh one thing that i
i'm going to emphasize underline in this
session is that it doesn't need to lead
i mean this model relativity it doesn't
need to lead to
uh dawn right materialism about
uh theories of brain and cognitive
system i mean
model relativity is not all about
taking an untreatable attitude toward
brain science but at the same time
so the the old goal the old project is
to end up with some sort of
subtler
perspective on scientific realities
about cognitive science and
and
the brain science
you for the context welcome
dean if you'd like to
say hello and um if you have any
opening shots to fire
i i don't have any opening shots of fire
my name's dean
i'm in calgary i'm uh sorry for coming
in late but my
link was sending me off into another
corner of the uh
universe so glad i'm here thanks for uh
thanks for being here majido really glad
that you're
here to talk about this paper i found
the paper fantastic
pleasure is all mine
so modularity
i mean it's in the title
modularity models
and then the free energy
um
and then the tale of two architectures
which was a little bit of a reference
towards the tale of two densities
another active
paper
so um
just
how would you
reframe the argument of hippolyto and
kirchoff
majeed and where do you think like in 22
what can we say now that we couldn't
have said
in 2019
oh well
what
well i do not think that we could say
anything more than we were saying in
2019 because all of the actual stuff was
there i think that this is something
that
comes with philosophy because uh no
information has been added
as a matter of fact i just elaborated on
the
information that was there in terms of
the argument from intransitivity and
all of that discussion of uh
causal modelling and dynamical modeling
and all that so
uh i don't think that any actual
information has been added the only
thing that has been
elaborated on was the emphasis on the
rule of the modeler the
uh which if we insist on
uh so
as i was watching this in the previous
discussion of
uh of uh the same paper in active
inference lab
uh and uh
i was so
dean's discussion of the
in terms of the bob alice
uh metaphor the discussion of the
perspective of the observer the
observer that is watching both
bob and alice
uh interested me very much so if i want
to rephrase the discussion of the
modeler in terms of information here we
can as well
start
real estate that's in terms of the
observer but
uh i think i don't think that the point
is that technical the point is rather
philosophical than scientific or formal
in terms of information theory so
uh no actual information has been added
during these two years only and i think
that this approach is gaining momentum
this emphasize on the rule of
uh modeler or interpreter is uh
drawing even
more
this uh is leading to even more
discussions in the free energy principle
literature
i totally agree with that point and then
blur dean um
it made me think of quantum
and how the
double slit experiment kind of kicking
and screaming
has taken 100 years
in that one limited setting
to consider the role of the observer
even though it's really complex thing we
won't go into it but we'll talk about
quantum and fep um in a few weeks but
that was like the anomaly
that signaled yeah you need to take the
observer into account as part of the
measuring apparatus
very quantitative empirical observation
that there was a non-negotiable or um
irreducible role of the observer and
then on the qualitative side
the relational insight
that scientists are human and science is
a human activity
and um that
was not driven on
uh empirical observations of wave and
particle on a screen like the twin slit
was but it was just a sort of
low level philosophical argument that
there isn't a uh
a fungible role for the observer or the
modeler and so it is very interesting to
see how that has started to
catch on
and then how does that change the way we
do science
when that
is taken
[Music]
as like a starting point
that there's an observer
modeling the system
um so like that was in this diagram when
we started with um
just talking about like the functional
and the effective connectivity and then
the mechanism which is kind of not
either those
and then
it wasn't until the very end when we're
like oh but it's the scientist
projecting in
to this whole model that's another level
of
how we think about it we can't just like
all be sitting around just talking about
bob and alice
but then now there's going to be us with
multiple perspectives looking at the
scientists taking multiple perspectives
on bob and alice so are we stuck in this
sort of
subjective infinite regress
how are we going to salvage
cognitive realism
are you asking me
anyone
but if you have any thoughts definitely
go for it
i have some ideas but i i mean i prefer
if other
how about yeah dean and then majida than
blue if you want to
well
one of the things majid that i
that i took away from reading your paper
was
this is this is funny because
typically when i
when i pick something up it's pretty
foreign to me it starts out being way on
the other side of a markov blanket
and then i i guess i somehow alright i'm
able to sort of get inside of it and
relate it back to the things that i know
and eventually i get it
a bit of a grip on it and then next
thing you know there's
four duck rabbits um spinning madly out
of control on a
on a
on a gradient
but one of the things that i took away
from this was
um and i think i mentioned it in the in
the point one is
is
are you nine o'clocking when we're
taking these slices in time and we're
building these models
my
question was what are the specifics of
that i mean if if we take an fmri
image
i know the the machine itself that's
taking those slices of time
isn't necessarily conscious but it is
carrying out some sort of an
instantiation
exercise and so one of the things i
wanted to kind of talk to you a little
bit about
not necessarily on a quantum level but
one of the sections of your paper which
was really really influential to me
was a section on a golden thread
i wanted to i was hoping that perhaps
within that idea of partitioning
whether it's through quantum quantum
methodology or quantum series or
whatever
if you could maybe talk a little bit
about that that idea of what you meant
by a golden thread not just
metaphorically but maybe materially and
maybe
influentially if there is such a word
because that part of it
really mattered to me and i it actually
got me writing a whole set of sub notes
based on that section so maybe maybe you
could expand on that a little bit
because i think there's a lot there
thanks dean for the great question so
yes we'd love to learn more about the
golden thread
unmute and then continue i i thought
that uh so
very well uh so if i may do a bit of
advertisement uh i have been discussing
this specifically this specific issue
this dog rabbit thing in another paper
which is published in a philosophy
journal it is named cognitive
penetration and cognitive realism and it
is published in
in
episode it relates this issue to
uh the issue of theory ladenness in
philosophy of science works of thomas
green and all that but
uh so i can't uh so uh
well
what i say here so i'm also interested
in the relation between feb and quantum
theory and uh i'm i'm working on a
project that relates steps to cubism in
as one of the significant
interpretations of quantum mechanics but
uh in this context uh i cannot so
the paper is not directly related or
even indirectly to quantum mechanic and
the rule of observer i
rather take some sort of
so if i want to say this in more
technical terms i would use
shannon's theory of information to
uh to articulate the rule of the
observer a bit clearer so
about the question if i understand it
correctly what happens
when the picture rotates and
there's a scanning of some sort of
scanning is taking place
whether
uh
so
i correctly understand
that your question is about what happens
when there is a rotation but there is no
observer to
uh want to work out whether it is a dog
or a rabbit right
and then the whole business of so so
when we're trying to encapsulate
something and you you spoke
clearly in the in the paper about we we
don't necessarily have to see this as a
as a hard and fast edges kind of thing
we can kind of appreciate that there's a
certain amount of fuzziness that's
actually enabling our conversation
and so that because the lines aren't
abrupt
and and when we do decide to put a
markov blanket around something it's us
choosing to do that at a certain scale
with a certain amount of specificity and
steven sillett in the point one talked
about so what what is available at a
meso scale
so that golden thread business that what
do we last sue
what is that fmri actually
trying to entail that's what i was
hoping that you could maybe tease out
for us a little bit very well also uh i
can't be all clear about that because
being a philosopher i'm a bit naive
about neuroimaging and that sort of
stuff but
as some sort of general insight and
trivial insight from philosophy of
science i would say that it would depend
on what we are trying to trace by using
a fmri or any other observational device
or measurement so
and
the fact that we could use this
measurement devices in a number of
different ways and by by devices i do
not only refer to actual devices but
also theoretical devices such as markov
blankets and that sort of stuff so and
applying that to different scales and
different different levels doesn't
need to mean that there is no object
effect of matter to be represented by
these devices so
uh i might be able to use different
theoretical and mathematical devices to
measure the
space of my room uh i may be able to use
for example
kilometers i or i may be able to use
with noodles or something of that sort
and uh
this doesn't mean that there is no fact
of matter to be
to be
measured after all we can see this
picture in terms of either
rabbit or
a duck but not as a dog or a cow for
example and whether we see it as a dark
or rabbit again is influenced by so
uh it i would say that to some extent it
will depend on the original
vagueness of the picture to what extent
the subjectivity to what extent
can affect the perception what we see
is a matter of
uh the target system itself the
properties of the target system itself
so
[Music]
i mean no matter how hard we drive we
could hardly be able to see this duck or
rabbit as a cow or a dog or something
else but at the same time to some extent
especially when the target system allows
for some
vagueness to some extent or
presuppositions or
goals and
intentions be around the actual
situation and
uh
so there is some sort of constraint or a
moderate amount of theoreticalness to
use a jargon by philosophy philosophers
of science that is taking place here
but
it doesn't mean that there is no
i mean it doesn't need to
strip the target
of all of its objective features
i still i i'm still not sure whether i
could address your worry correctly or
not because i couldn't see the point
about the
fmri and neuroimaging techniques so
well all i was i guess i'm kind of
i'm agreeing with the argument that
you're putting forward which is that any
time we make an observation and then we
drop some kind of a representation we
call that a model
even in those even in those efforts to
try to be precise we have to leave open
a little bit of latitude a little bit of
wiggle room
because
as you pointed out you can have a
dynamic causal model and to get into an
argument whether or not that's the
appropriate model it should be an
acyclic one
right for example that was what you were
saying and
that kind of gets you going down a path
of arguing about
which is the right
tool as opposed to saying do tools
leverage
right i think that's what maybe that's
what i was reading into
what you were trying to say
that's all
thanks dean um blue and then majeed
so i think this kind of goes into um
what dean was saying about
scale-friendly versus scale-free and so
like with a markov blanket and with like
this um
you know
uh denotation of a module whether it's
vertical or horizontal uh a horizontal
or vertical mod module
um
you know we impute the markov blanket on
whatever scale we're trying to
separate conditionally
so i just wanted to to bring that that
point um
back in and also um that this idea of
maybe like
in incomplete
partitioning
so i mean if there was a a complete
partition around each module um there
would be like no ability to transfer
information from module to module
and in the brain i mean we do know that
that definitely um
some
the pieces have to communicate to make
the entire brain or it wouldn't be
considered an organ you know we wouldn't
be able to mark off blanket you know
these this idea of nested markov
blankets so i don't know about this
information encapsulation or or
information
leakiness magetta would be nice if you
um maybe kind of
unpacked that a little bit more for us
yes the information encapsulation
topic
so uh the thing is that i can't see uh
for some reason i can't see you in this
picture and i have to shift to the
youtube page in order to see you and
it's called you can maybe go to on the
bottom bar toggle tile view
there's like i use that but
it's all right
it's for some reason i can't see that
there are pages of people but i cannot
just see your faces it is
it shows
d the initial
and b
it may have to do with what countries
we're all in which is totally fine at
least we have audio
let me try it once more with well oh yes
at least we have audio so very well
so uh
uh
well about information encapsulation uh
shelley ex try to explain that in terms
of that bob alice metaphor
great
yeah information encapsulation as
applied to the bob alice
parable all right very well so
for one thing this information
encapsulation is one of the features of
uh jerry fodor's original statement of
uh the thesis of modularity and so
uh
which which is quite uh
flexible a flexible thesis and motives
so
for me
in the way that i see that
model relativity
entails this kind of
modularity information encapsulation
because in order to have model and again
it can be stated in terms of market
blankets and whether the mark of
blankets are embodied or nested or not
is itself another issue but the very
fact that we can use markov blanket or
markovian models it indicates that we
can we are able to set some sort of
in
barriers conditional independence
between
uh internal and external spaces so in
order to state this free energy
principle of crystalline there's uh
interpret these spaces in terms of
active spaces and sensory spaces but at
the same time it indicates that there is
some sort of barrier even though if the
barrier is conditional and probabilistic
i do not think that for information
encapsulation we need anything stronger
than
this kind of
flexible conditional barrier between
inside and outside or between different
spaces
and this is the point that uh so when i
was watching your discussion in the
previous uh session zero three five
point one uh i saw that this metaphor of
bob and
alice came out and there was the
question of whether there is any sort of
cause or relation between them and
whether the relation between them is
anyway correlated so as i argued in the
paper they may be some sort of causal
relation or correlation uh
which can be stated in terms of internal
interventionist approaches which are of
course liable to
their own uh
to other sorts of criticism that we
don't
need to discuss right though but
uh
i think that information encapsulation
doesn't need anything that stronger than
the general model relativity that i
tried to advertise advocate in this
paper so the main point is that
regardless of whether or not there is
any kind of causal relation
actual relationship between the actions
of bob and the actions of uh alice or
perhaps i have to call them
uh
charles and lucy in order to
be more loyal to the ruler to the
soul of
the tale of two cities uh the thing is
that to the extent that the information
in each unit is not available accessible
to the other unit we can speak of
information encapsulation and then we
are making models i mean if we can't set
any kind of distinction between internal
and
external spaces and if we can't in the
same way that we may not be
able to set a distinction between models
and their targets there wouldn't be any
modeling practice there wouldn't be any
scientific activity on the other hand if
we are able to set a distinction between
internalized external
or any kind of distinction between
uh
models and their target
we would be able to
to state some sort of conditional
barrier
it still doesn't indicate that there is
no kind of information
uh
so it setting the barrier by itself
doesn't show that the information in one
block is not available to the other
black but
uh the yeah and i can't see the uh
yeah
i i was fascinated by this picture when
i was watching your discussion in the
previous session so uh in terms of the
relationship between bob and alice the
action of bob brushing the teeth is
a correlated with what alice does in the
other
unit but it has been assumed that the
information in the unit is not available
the information in bob unit is not
available to alice and vice versa even
though the information
may be available to us as observers or
if we
contrive another observer a third person
the information might be available to
her to the observer but to the extent
that the information in each unit is not
available to the person in the other
units i think that we can speak of some
sort of partial information
encapsulation
thanks very
uh
interesting
if we couldn't i just really like
calling that part about how if we
couldn't make a distinction between the
target system and the model
between the territory and the map then
it's not modeling so it's kind of like
well when you kick a football does it
model a parabola well it doesn't have
the
modeling the self model the integrated
world model whatever one wants to call
it such that it is just
the actual causal relationships that
it's engaging in the world and no more
whereas
cognitive entities
like scientists
are engaging in
[Music]
modeling and then that means that they
are able to engage in counter factuals
in thinking through other minds
they are reducing their uncertainty
from
a partial information encapsulation
view
and sometimes you get more information
than the system has
available
but other times it's radically less
and so it's kind of like an application
of a markov blanket partitioning
with some
non-markov concepts from philosophy of
science
to the scientists investigating target
systems
getting partial measurements that's
their observations coming in
and then they're updating their hidden
state inference
about what they think is happening the
likelihood of different hypotheses
just like any active entity would
well if i may elaborate a bit more on
this and it returns to the question of
cognitive realism uh i think that
despite speaking of all of this model
relativity it doesn't need to lead to
some sort of global or
uh general form of anti-realism because
well uh a part of my activity in the
past years was
dedicated to developing some sort of
cognitive reality that is based on flip
assuming that the practice of scientific
model making is underpinned by
the dynamical interaction between
scientists or groups of scientists and
their environment so
this kind of model relativity
i mean the relation between free energy
principle and
model based science is very complicated
and it is not something that is directly
related to this aspect of them of this
paper but this paper is a piece of a
larger project that has been
finding its own shape in the past few
years and it is about the
uh as i say the general idea here is
that in the same even though
the free energy principle the
theoretical framework experimental
activity that
is embodied in the research stream that
leads to the development of free energy
principle
is
basically some sort of model based
scientific activity on the other hand if
you are interested in explaining
scientific activity and scientific model
making and if you are naturalist we are
interested in finding good natural
explanations for that we have to look
into the underpinning natural mechanism
that makes scientific model making
possible right and a good place to look
for that is
the scientific accounts of the
interaction between the agent the
organism and the environment and because
free energy principle provides a viable
account of the relation between agents
or as i discussed in my more recent work
a group of agents which is the community
of scientists and their environment both
social environment and biological
environment we can as well grow in
scientific model making in the
mechanisms of free energy principles so
the situation is quite complicated and
runs in both direction
we like running in both
directions
so i guess that's okay
um
so we have a few different
ways we could go dean or blue do you
want to ask a question or we can go to
one that we've previously written down
can i ask a quick question daniel yes
yeah so
in the in the point one blue brought up
something that i'm still sort of
trying to untangle when she talked she
was asking about genes in particular and
how it might relate to what
this paper was
potentially pointing to at least it
raised the specter around the idea
of so
information encapsulation
do we need time in order for us to be
able to take a measure or put a boundary
around
or encapsulate or somehow
mark in a markovian way
decide where the partition is
and
so
i'm still trying to figure out whether
or not
we are talking about
a world where because i think a world
exists where there are two things going
into
not necessarily
the same direction we got one thing
where we look at the world and we ask
ourselves whether something was
completed we do a completion analysis we
take an account and i think models
fit nicely into that world what i
thought this paper
raised some some ideas around was
is that half of the if is that half of
the whole picture is the other half
do models and and being modular allow us
to include
or make sure that we have included
everything that we need in order to be
able to get the best sense of what's on
the other side of that divide so when
we're making these inferences we can use
models as a way to account for things
but are we also able to project off of
that and and sort of make better guesses
better inferences
i've used that i've used the expression
prediction matter expert and so i i was
wondering again
those words weren't exactly used in this
paper but was that part of what we were
trying to sort of dig down to is it is
it is it just a matter of
people use models people people's models
account for things in in in certain ways
but they also if we don't get too hung
up on the precision of that account they
can also be
sort of fuzzy and left
semi-open and give us an opportunity to
also be creative and decide
essentially whether or not we have
enough information to make that next
best guess so just kind of wondering
about that
yes please all right very well that's a
that's a very brilliant point so uh it
it comes back to the issue of
completeness of models their accuracy
certainty and that sort of stuff and
completely agree so
uh it uh
it has been taken for granted and i
think that part of it
part of this interest has been rised by
richard levine's uh paper the strategy
of model-based science in population
biology that we are making models but
the accuracy of models is very important
so the models have to be accurate enough
to represent uh to do the
representational task well and
they have to be complete in the sense
that they have to be detailed you know i
think that this is very good point but
look
uh how much
accuracy is enough i mean we can speak
of completeness of models but
uh absolutely complete models i think
that uh i've been reading a shorter
story from a north and american uh
writer the on the executive of science
or something like that which is the
story of people in an empire who are
trying model map makers cartographers
who are trying to make maps of the
empire and they are very obsessive they
want to have conflict maps but they end
up with having maps that are
oh all right perfect poor house yes yes
precisely so they end up with having
maps that are as big as the empire
itself so
uh then at least so and it's completely
true that
levin's two speak of accuracy and
detailedness of models but
uh then again
uh
completeness in it so details i mean
more details are not necessarily leading
to better models because accuracy works
only in combination with some other
virtues such as
generality and precision of predictions
so
even though
uh so the other question is that home
how to find how to strike the right
balance
between generality one hand and accuracy
and precision of models on the other
hand and i'm tempted to say that i
understand that i'm just trying to point
to the same direction to speaking of the
rule of modal scientific models and
model making but then again how much
precision and
accuracy have to be taken into account
and
have to be related to
uh have to put
in harmony with generality again i would
i'm tempted to say that it is again a
matter of interest and explanatory and
predictive goals of the model maker
so
i will ask a question from the live chat
from stephen
so stephen majeed was curious about your
understanding of
the relationship in which practitioners
seek to apply low dimensional
computational modeling with other scales
of knowing in uncertain and dynamic
environments
so for example there's the awareness and
the perception of the duck rabbit
and then there are the affordances
in our niche that go beyond just sort of
a visual toy example
so open-ended question about what um
you might think about that kind of
application of modeling perhaps in a
social setting
do the models in the social setting need
to be dimensional or what if i see that
in terms of the relation between
dynamical causal models and
dags so for example i
assume that dags could provide some sort
of low dimensional model that is capable
of representing the network aspects or
something like that
yeah i think that's a
good
question i mean continue with that and
i'll write some things down
all right very well so uh
uh so
uh
i'd like to i'm tempted to repeat this
uh well
i think that it provides a good example
so
take the verb of social relation or
social events that we may want to model
so
this provides actually a good nice
example of multi-scale or
multi-scale nature of target phenomena
so this
uh the social events
is constituted by the relationship
between people and event and environment
and uh well people are actual human
being they are
biological entities constitute of
uh
people who are
self-organizing system and we are able
to explain people and their behavior at
some level
on the basis of
uh
biological facts so we may be uh able to
use
some sort of modeling system that are
applicable in biology or that sort of
stuff but at a larger scale when we try
to model the relation between different
people as nodes in networks and that
sort of stuff we may need to change our
modeling device to
i don't know
devices that are good at representing
uh a small board networks or that sort
of stuff
if that
does make any sense i think that i just
get confused by the point about low
dimensionality of models
in social systems but
um
[Music]
it could be a steven ism or one way at
least that i would read that would be
like the
maps that we make are lower dimensional
than the territories they have a
different resolution but also they don't
consider they're not trying to be a full
inventory of every variable in the
system like there might be a thousand
chemicals circulating in our blood but
then somebody might make a lower
dimensional model with just blood sugar
or two-dimensional model with just you
know cortisol and blood sugar
and um
[Music]
i think it's uh
an active inference
open question when we make lower
dimensional models of complex
multi-scale target phenomena like you
addressed
um
[Music]
it
uh i mean i don't want to jump to and
answer but it seems clear like that the
philosophical
implications of a lower dimensional map
shouldn't be confused with
systems accounting of the territory
because
it's
not the same thing
and um yeah steven just followed up in
the chat he just said generally how does
majeed see the informational or physical
sense of systems
like some people talk about systems in
the more ontological sense about the
parts and how they're connected
other times we're talking about systems
informationally
like our analysis of the measurement
data and so the system like the default
mode network is a connectivity pattern
that isn't necessarily the anatomical
connection so how do we think about
these different kinds of systems
and maybe where does the fep come into
play with that
all right very well uh uh that's a very
good question so i'm a tag you're a
structural realist so i'm committed to
some sort of information theoretic
ontology and i think that uh
well and i say that i'm defending some
sort of embodied informational uh
structure realism so
uh
when i say that i was advocating
cognitive realism it was it would have
been more precise to say that i'm
advocating cognitive search or realism
which is actually the title of the book
that i wrote about this topic so
uh
and what rule free energy principle
plays in this context uh is a very
complex rule so let's assume that we
have the structure of scientific
theories or scientific models on the one
hand so let's assume that we have a
class of models
or scientific models on on the one hand
and on the other hand we have or causal
structure of the word which is or target
system something that we are trying to
represent by or scientific model so uh
when i speak about a structural realism
uh i think that it has been the official
wisdom of philosophy of science for the
past
uh 15 years or so and
people were trying to use different kind
of
formal
vehicles such as set theory model theory
category theory to speak of this
representational relation between the
class of models and the causal structure
of the world right but i uh so my beef
with that was that the
formal relations such as isomorphism do
not contribute to strengthening realism
because
these formal models such as isomorphism
are not informed to i mean you can use
isomorphism to relate
any two sets together provided that
there have enough number of set members
so it doesn't contribute to
uh realism much so what i was trying to
do was to use feb free energy principle
to account for the class of models and
their target system in the world
assuming that
scientists are
self-organizing system that aim at
minimizing the
discrepancy between their models and
their target system in the real world so
uh but it is my take i mean it is
something that i'm trying to develop i
won't i don't say that this is the
uh
this is a very well uh this is not the
orthodox view either in the philosophy
of science common commodity or in the
flip community but i think that
uh when we speak of representation in
terms of the representational capacity
of the model of models in terms of the
relation between class of models
and causal structure in the world
free energy principle can play a very
subtle and
a specific rule there
maybe we're in a little strange neck of
the woods but i think having
scientists as real entities
doing something
seems at home
here
blue
so i think you presented us with a lot
of things that don't contribute to
realism but is there anything that you
think does contribute to realism
[Music]
well
could you elaborate cbs uh i mean uh
because of the model relativity or
because of free energy principle
well well so like in in terms of
cognitive structural realism like what
what
does provide evidence for the cognitive
structural realist argument i mean like
you've given us a lot of things that
you've deconstructed that but is there
can you take the opposite side and
provide evidence for cognitive
structural realism or
fair enough
uh look
the general
i think that the general arguments for
scientific realism in general have been
always stated in some sort of
uh numerical arguments assuming that if
science was not representing the
structure of reality it would be a
matter of cosmic co in the empirical
adequacy of science has been a matter of
cosmic
coincidence so there are some sort of
uh arguments usual arguments in the
philosophy of science that try to
relate empirical adequacy of scientific
theories to
approximate truth of scientific theories
right and
uh structural realism just tries to
model this representational relation the
veracity of or variety verity called
representational relations in terms of
say theory and modal theory so in my
view it would be more realistic to
consider scientists as actual human
being constitute by flesh and blood who
aim at minimizing the
discrepancy between their models and the
world i would say that the evidence that
i could provide for this take on realism
uh
could be
has its roots in uh evolutionary biology
because
uh if
if we had not been successful in
minimizing the discrepancy between our
models
reality we would also fail to maximize
or survey well so
uh i think that i can in as a way of
evidence or argument i can try to
ground the argument the usual scientific
realist argument that aim to relate the
empirical adequacy of science to truths
of theories i can try to
relate the or success to maximizing or
survival as an evidence of
or success in minimizing the discrepancy
between our scientific models and their
target system the causal structure of
reality
thanks that also plays into some other
discussions we've been having about like
the objective function of science and
this sort of multi-scale nature that
scientific fields research labs and
organizations and individuals are
engaged in
pragmatic and epistemic
actions and so in active inference we
have this
scale-friendly approach which a priori
doesn't require a specific scale of
analysis which is what you brought up
with markov blankets
and
any specific application
will entail a specific scale of analysis
because it's empirical and so it's this
uh one foot in both world just like
linear models are
the model doesn't have uh a priori scale
but then when we specify it we do make
it specific and what's interesting about
active is that we could think about this
action and perception loop
of different kinds of nested entities
now definitely it's going to get complex
for any nested entity
and then it brings a whole other level
with a strange loop
and the meta modeling and the cognizer
and the thinking about oneself that's
like a whole another level
but just
a way to talk about vertically and
horizontally interacting
systems is an awesome start
so blue
and then uh
either majeed you could respond to what
blue says or dave feel free to say hello
i just wanted to
compliment you on that awesome like
prelude to like next week's discussion
about modeling ourselves right so like
it's a very interesting
perspective when when the modeler is the
model is the modeler is the model it's a
loop
cool um dave would you like to say hello
or ask anything
or hi um nothing particular to ask i'm
sorry to be late i've been in
marinating myself in neuropsychoanalysis
for the last week and a half so that's
my closest i've got to an excuse for
being late
fair enough
um
so
let's go to a few of the other topics
that we had written down
so i think before we get to this more
the
the liftoff on the post dot 2
let's talk a little bit about
intransitivity
because in our discussions we had looked
at intransitivity in a preference
framework where intransitivity of
preferences has been transformational in
microeconomics for example
and then there's intransitivity from a
game theoretic perspective
like the rock paper scissors and just
strategic intransitivity which also
brings us back to
the population biology modeling but you
were discussing um intransitivity in a
specific context which is about the
predictive processing architectures
and models of cognitive architecture so
could you maybe unpack a little bit what
does untrans intransitivity
mean in that context who disagrees
what would be different if it weren't
that way
uh yeah sure so
uh
i think that the uh so uh
the thing is that
if we assume that there is translativity
information could be transferred from
one unit to another
uh
we would have a serious problem in
defending uh i was thinking of saying
something more about active inference
and objective inferences because but i
will put that in the background for the
time being but the thing is that
uh the point that i was trying to make
in the
paper was that this all of this talk
about uh the distinction between
transitivity and intransitivity only
works with regard to
uh
invoking a specific kind of model which
is no wonder because the paper is about
the significance of scientific models so
we can defend
transitivity or intransitivity of the
cognitive structure depending on the
kind of modeling that we summon so if we
assume that the only kind of
models that are
allowable in the context of free energy
principle or dynamical causal models we
will end up by
a straightforward rejection of
modularity but this doesn't need to be
the case because free energy principle
is not all about
uh representing the actual causal
mechanisms neurophysiological mechanisms
of the brain so uh this is as much about
representing this neurophysiological
structures as the general properties of
the the
it is as much
about representing the local significant
uh neurophysiological mechanism as it is
about explaining the relation between
different units and different component
counterparts that are uh implemented in
the brain so it is supposed to be
a theory a unifying theory of the brain
and
in some sense it may indicate that we do
not need modularity enough because if we
want to defend some sort of unity
between different
components between different parts of
the structure we do not need to be able
to
modulate the brain and the paper tries
to argue the reverse that
speaking of the connection between
different parts
in terms of mainly in terms of
and again it comes back to the
distinction between effective
functionality and functional
connectivity that you discuss very well
most probably better than i would be
able to in the previous session
would be a matter of uh
the
kind of uh properties of the cognitive
system that we aim to model by invoking
free energy principle whether there are
local properties of the brain or the
global unifying properties of the brain
and if you want to
model the brain in its unity we also
need to be able to speak about the
connection between different parts and
from the very fact that we assume that
there are different parts
uh it follows that we have to
assume that there is some sort of
encapsulation or a weak point a moderate
form of modularity
very interesting thank you any other
thoughts on that
well then i'm going to go to a hard
question which is
what makes a model active inference
is that a uh
in the in the circle or out of the
circle is it a binary classifier
is it a zero to one scale
what will happen when people disagree
does simply any model involving action
and inference
qualify as active inference
um
[Music]
we have asked it on a few previous
discussions and i think we've gotten a
range of answers but it's definitely an
important one to
revisit from this
model-based science
perspective
well i mean i have been defending some
sort of pan psychism i have been
marshaling free energy principle in
defense of versions of pan psychism so
uh i'm tempted to say that any kind of
self-organizing system that can minimize
the discrepancy between its internal
models and the environment
is capable of forming active inferences
but
uh
it is not directly to
i mean it is not specifically related to
this issue of modal relativity unless we
assume that
uh
model
relativity is quite obvious it is
everywhere in scientific activity i
cannot find any specific relation
between
that kind of
pan psyches account of active inference
and a specific discussion of model
relativity
dana can ask a question
yep dean and then blue
sorry blue maybe you want to go first
you put your hand up and i just blurted
out go ahead dean
okay sorry about that thanks
so in at the end of the last of the last
live stream there was a question posted
in the live chat about so does active i
know maybe this ties in with what you
were just asking daniel does active
inference what does active inference
tell us about the model of the person
trying to kick the ball
and i'm i'm curious about this
because
you wrote another paper with a you
co-authored a paper on active inference
and abduction with somebody if i
pronounced their last name incorrectly i
apologize p pia taranin
and and
i'm kind of curious because i think what
active inference enacting an active
inference within model building
and modularity is it it
it gets us asking a question much like
charles saunders pierce would ask if you
walked in late on bob and alice
okay
it's nine o'clock but you're not really
paying attention to the clock right now
you just walk to into a room and there's
on the other side of the one-way mirror
is a is a subdivided two two cubes one
with bobbin and one with alice in it but
you've you've walked in
and you don't have a model yet other
than the fact that you're on the other
side of the curtain you don't have a
smiley face or a frowny face what you
have is
a moment where you have to ask
if you're actively inferring and you're
enacting this is
what should i be surprised if and what
should i not be surprised if as the as
the as the stuff that's carrying out in
bob's room
somehow is
appears to not being carried out in
alice's room
so
i don't know that that modeling
can can sort of segregate itself out
scale free
from the idea of of the specifics like
pierce would say if you walked in and
into a room and somebody opposite of you
had a bunch of white beans in their left
hand and a bag of beans in their right
hand and asked you as the person walking
to the room
did these beans in this one hand come
from this bag
you wouldn't have enough information
to be able to give a specific
and clear
answer to that but you could start a
process of modeling
you could start
a modularity exercise to try and gather
from an an abductive
sense what what what led up to this
moment and so i'm just kind of wondering
how do you how how you take this paper
and and
that example and sort of tie it in with
some of the
other work that you've been
because i i'm hoping maybe i'll talk to
you after this but maybe i would like to
be able to review your active inference
and abduction paper as well if you have
time
anyway i'm just wondering what because i
think if we're looking at this from
active inference and enacting sometimes
we walk in and we walk in and we have to
infer based on a limited amount of
information and so i think that's what
we're trying to do
we're basically saying when we walk in
do or don't be surprised if and then
whatever plays out
approximately on the on those time
scales next
what do you agree with
yes
i do agree and
uh
well uh i'm very happy that you uh
mentioned that paper because i wanted to
speak about that too earlier so the
thing is that as i say there are two
phases of the same project so in this
project i mean in the project that has
been
uh stated in this uh a tale of two
architectures and in another paper a
critical analysis of mark kobe and
monism i was emphasizing the modal base
modal relative nature of active
inference as an activity
uh but the main reason why i was getting
interested in that because of the mark
of blankets because i think that marco
blankets are also very
strong and uh
reliable modeling tools also for the
general scientific modeling purposes so
it is the other side of my project when
i'm trying to ground scientific realism
and scientific model making in active
inference and free energy principles so
this is the other side and
uh
going back to the general arguments for
scientific realism again a strong
version of the defense of scientific
realism uh is reliant on invoking uh
infra
explanatory inferences by developing
something that is called
uh inference to the best explanation and
this project that you mentioned the
paper that has been written by me and
arty and there is another paper
uh we were collaborating on another
paper uh on the same subject aims to
show that how the general explanatory
inferences how the general
abduction is
grounded in the process of active
inferences right so
i think that there are two sides of the
same coin and there are two intertwined
two interrelated
uh projects but uh
as i say i do not see uh so
do you want to also explore the uh
implications what of that for the
metaphor of bob and alice i mean do you
think that it has any specific
ramifications for this
bob and alice metaphor
yeah that's that was
that's exactly what i think it does and
again it's a separate paper
and it's another excellent excellent
insight if you if you get a chance to
read it but i think when we're trying to
figure out what's effective and
functional
we we come in to a situation looking at
bob and alice
and and over time
our model grows as well right and i
think that's part of where
my question about what is
what is scale free
yes bob and alice are in their cubicles
and those cubes are of the same
dimensions and then there's a scale
friendly part that kind of grows over
those slices of time so yes i i actually
do think that it would be interesting to
sort of say when when did we walk in on
this
bob analysis observation
very well so i would say that for the uh
moderate weak sense of encapsulation
that is at issue in this specific paper
a tale of two city uh it would be the
the necessary condition is that the
information in each unit is not
available to them to the person in the
other unit or in the other black so
uh to the extent that the information
about for example bob brushing his teeth
is not available to alice there is some
sort of weak encapsulation and i think
that it is you know for
establishing some sort of
uh
moderate uh modulation but the other
part the uh the more fundamental uh the
more fundamental question about the
uh scale relativity and to what extent
so
it is some sort of scientific fact that
we can choose this scale that we need on
the basis of our explanatory interests
so at this specific setting my
explanatory interest my scientific
interest was to
come to to set the limits of the scale
at the
level of the rooms of bob and alice
because i wanted to explain
encapsulation so in another situation so
assume that you are an information
theorist and you want to develop a
general theory of communication between
these two units so you it is natural for
you to take the point of view of the
third person of another observer and
then there might be another person who
wants to speak about the relation
between this third person and the target
system and a techno so it made it might
go observer observer all the way up and
observable
uh all the way down and it would be a
matter of
uh what you are trying to do with
changing the scale what what goal do you
aim to achieve so
again at some papers i i was trying to
stay limited to the level of individual
so for example when i wanted to
model the activity of a scientist
specifics an individual scientist i was
focusing on the processes of
minimization of
uh
predictive uh predictions at the level
of individuals but at points i wanted to
model the behavior or speak about the
behavior of all scientific commodities
assuming that scientific practice is a
social act and i was
for that reason i was trying to expand
the limits of the scale and apply that
to the old community of scientists or a
specific group of scientists rather than
individual scientists what was important
for me and what i think is important is
to have
good and satisfactory justifications for
changing the level to be able to explain
clearly
what was the purpose of changing the
level taking it to
an upper level or a lower level and i
think that
to the extent that we are speaking about
encapsulation and modulation it is
justifiable to
limit the module to the specific cells
in which bob and alice are dwelling
so just wrote a few things down and
maybe this
captures it but the free energy
principle especially as you're
applying it in this um
[Music]
embodied informational and cognitive
structural realism perspective the fep
as a
theory of things is providing the
conceptual continuity for modeling
different complex systems including
scientists in the world and other
processes as they engage in their niche
and then the active inference
uh
framework we can say
is operationalizing this imperative for
persistence of different systems
and then connecting that
a priori process ontology
to
a whole host of other
patterns motifs
that we uh must explain in the world
like abduction
in the social and
communication case
and narrative information inference
on one end of us but then on the other
end we also want to have active
really dial in and get at exact
inference in certain cases where it's
like we made the fmri measurements and
we kind of want to like
leave philosophy
in the lab
and just plug and chug this pipeline
and we don't want that to be a pipeline
of nowhere
or um we don't want the output of the
pipeline to be interpreted in a
fallacious philosophical
milieu
but
at the same time
if we try to take that philosophical
baggage through every step
of the processor and the ram and the gpu
we get into these little nano debates
which you highlighted which is like
people
arguing whether cyclic or directed
acyclic
graphical models have philosophical
impact
when they're both just models that
scientists chose
for different reasons
uh i have to say that you have the knock
of explaining my ideas far more clearly
than i can so
here's my everybody majidi is a
brilliant young man
here's my next question for you because
there's multiple
fep
um frontiers here you have the book
then there's the markovian monism that
we had earlier discussed
the abduction one which we haven't
gotten a chance to discuss this paper
obviously
so
how do you keep the information
organized or
assess how new
papers coming in
play into how you want to develop these
different threads of research or
determine where
you can be making an impact
by targeting this paper or assessing
this phenomena or stepping into this you
know 5 000 year old philosophical debate
well uh
it is very hard to uh explain where
these ideas are coming from i mean
well i do not i mean if i could
state the process in this fashion i most
probably i would be able to hire someone
to write a program that does this
instead of doing that myself so
uh i think that it is mainly a matter of
intuition although it is
it is very ironical because
philosophically i'm not
someone who
uh
escorts too much credit by the intuition
so
uh but i think that i have a general
program as and as i said i'm trying to
defend some sort of
moderate version of cognitive realism
that tries to account for scientific
representation to grow scientific
representation in
uh in the relationship between uh set a
commodity of self-organizing agents and
their environment so
i think that i'm starting from the
uh uh from the uh simpler bits so for
example starting by just stating the
point that scientific representation
could be grounded in free energy
principle and then i'm just fleshing out
the
uh
other complex issues so for example
wanting so as they say one thing leads
to another as soon as you try to
account for scientific representation in
terms of free energy principle
uh people
point out and there have been excellent
papers by
excellent criticism for example by
uh uh max jones who were pointing out
this criticism that science is not an
individual activity it is a social
activity and then i am going back to
play showed the social aspects of my
view so i think that it is again some
sort of dynamical social
uh process that leads to development of
these ideas and then i'm trying to deal
with this social aspect
uh i
stumble on reading thomas kuhn and i see
that i have to also take care of theory
lateness for example and i engage with
that issue but i think that i started to
work on these applying this
model
relativity the
model based nature of scientific
activity to philosophy of mind since
2016 and then
as i say
one thing led to another and i'm where i
am now and i'm i have no idea
what impact would this project lead to
what group what group of people because
most probably the project is a bit too
scientific for philosophers and a bit
too philosophical for scientists but
uh well
it is
the only way that
i know for developing my philosophical
ideas
awesome thank you blue if you wanted to
raise your hand otherwise uh go for it
if not and then uh okay blue then dave
um
so i think my comment was it's kind of
old at this point but but really like
i was just curious about um
linking
this
or or under what
circumstances or how can we apply this
um
the active inference framework to um
partially
encapsulated systems
and so i mean i think that this is it
gets into like i i guess that's the big
question right so always just i would
love to hear your thoughts on
how information is passed from module to
module or or
what is this idea of mutual information
um you know in the collective uh pan
psychism sense like how do you think or
to what degree is it shared and can you
perhaps
maybe shed some light on mathematically
ways that you think it would make sense
to talk about
partial encapsulation
uh well uh so
starting from from the last part i think
that mathematical representation is
rather the easier part so
we can easily
model this
partial encapsulation by invoking some
sort of
uh partial isomorphism so it is enough
to have two sets of models and try
to and try to show that to what extent
or through what relation what parts what
subparts of these sets are related to so
to
uh what subsets of the other system uh
to the extent that there are
significant chunks that are not related
together through some sort of isomorphic
relation we can retain some sort of
partial isomorphism the other way i
think that the more other more intuitive
way of doing that is by invoking markov
blankets i think that as a matter of
fact i think that
partial encapsulation is a direct uh
results ramification of invoking
markovian blankets because they are
setting
uh
some sort of conditional independence
between different chunks
uh right so uh
well
uh from the very fact that there is some
sort of partial encapsulation it doesn't
follow that there is no
uh
amount of transfer of information
between the tanks at all the only thing
thing that is necessary for retaining
this partial encapsulation is that
at a given moment there is no actual
so the only thing i think that the
necessary condition and it is very
minimal for retaining some sort of
partial encapsulation is that at any
given time information at one unit is
not accessible to the observer in the
other unit i think that this condition
could be satisfied quite easily it is
why i think that some sort of partial
uh encapsulation endures
despite the validity of kirchoff and
hippolyta arguments
thanks blue and then go ahead so so i
guess this is um
how how
so so my my question was probably
backwards so what about how is
information shared not is how do you
demonstrate information sharing as
opposed to information encapsulates in
encapsulation like if there's a markov
blanket we establish conditional
independence but like
where can we establish conditional
dependence or how can we establish
conditional dependence that's
the part that's that's really i'm
curious about sorry all right it's very
old so uh look uh the internal and
external estates or the
sensory and active states are related
together but the thing is that the
observer or if if you are encapsulated
inside the markov blanket you can
uh infer the properties of outside only
indirectly so what i was trying to do to
some extent is to instead of assuming
that the cognitive system is cons is
composed of markov blankets i try to put
myself inside the marker blanket
and see
uh how could i get access to information
that is outside the mark of blanket or
inside other mark of blanket and to the
extent that there is no
direct relation or the information is
not directly
accessible at a given time
i think that some sort of encapsulation
endures
it's like a
cup half full cup half empty
channel half open channel half closed
it's the two
extremes
complete integration
which
maybe doesn't even make any sense like a
solid-state drive i mean what would it
even mean if all the information were
connected to all the other information
at the same time and just not compatible
with the architectures of physical
systems
so
interesting thought experiments though
for total integration
and then any realized system
is either going to be
fully conditionally
independent entirely markov blanketed
um
[Music]
or there'll be some partial relation
and then part of the realism and
instrumentalism okay that partial
relation
can be an
edge like an effective or a functional
connectivity edge
which doesn't imply a causal role
it's a scientific projection uh
situationally
defined
edge
that's being inferred
in a specific statistics framework
and then there are
hidden states of the world of observers
who are supposing
causes
like hypotheses about how things happen
in the world and then they engage in all
kinds of studies like loss of function
gain of function
blinded research
those are protocols or affordances that
scientists engage in to reduce their
uncertainty about
this hypothesis
space
so it's a very
interesting area uh dave and then dean
right um
the
perfect lead into what i was going to
ask about the uh where you draw the
boundaries where you draw the um
the blankets is really important um
i like to say nasty things about donald
hoffman or or more specifically the way
he allows himself to be portrayed is
thinking that there's
absolute freedom and
throwing blankets wherever you want that
the boundaries are totally arbitrary and
so we are all one of the
really though uh blanketing is a matter
of where what's actually happening um
are you majeed familiar about there we
go are you familiar with mara beller's
work on the level of actual scientific
interaction
can you describe that work a little bit
mara bella yeah she was um for a number
of years she was perhaps the leading
historian of the early days of quantum
mechanics
and as she got more and more in depth
into what actually was happening there
are certain papers
uh by boar that are
widely as regarded as being totally
incomprehensible
you'd go from one thing that he's saying
in the paper to a few sentences later
and there doesn't seem to be any
connection at all and people are
thinking well what was he had he lost it
was he too tired when he gave this talk
well she went down and and trying to
take sentence by sentence and phrase by
phrase
asking the same question that a good
drama coach asks
for each statement that you have to
deliver
what question
is that speech an answer to
and she found if you went through the
people that that bore was in intimate
dialogue
with whether he was on their side or
being driven crazy but like einstein if
you kept that in mind and asked who is
he talking to who was born talking to
at each moment
everything became very straightforward
he was having a series of dialogues
with a dozen people
and just stringing one fragment of the
dialogue after another and
and i haven't read it yet but um that
totally ties in with the concept of
conversation theory which was something
put together in the 1960s and 70s by my
teacher
of cybernetic learning theory gordon
pask who defines the minimum unit of
consciousness as the conversation
and also
represents each conversation or at least
each enduring conversation as a
psychological individual
so you have very much nested markov
blankets you have very much
the leipnician hierarchy and the
indefinitely large or infinitely large
and deep hierarchy
of minds composed of minds composed of
minds
and
when the way beller presents that that's
what science is about
uh having lots of dialogues figuring out
how they fit together
the dialogues be getting new dialogues
and
uh in past sense those conversations
themselves in the best case become
the enduring individuals maybe the
immortal individuals that make up a
successful living science
well yeah
thank you very much for uh the input
yeah i agree that the
the
issue of choosing the scale is not
arbitrary so i think that earlier in the
paper i refer to
the works of rodolf carnap and thomas
kuhn to point out that i think that
there should be some general
considerations that rule over the choice
of a specific scale
this is partly
determined by the property of the target
system itself and partly by the interest
of the modeler depending on what the
model is trying to work out about the
target system so i completely agree with
that
and evolves the collaborative and uh
distributes it so uh
i don't know whether it is i'm reading
too much onto what you said right but
into what you said right now but
uh i'm completely on board the
uh some sort of
collective uh distributed take on
scientific activity and this is
something that i have been defending in
recent papers in the previous year so
uh i completely agree with that
and uh well
uh my
so the point about in individuals and
how to
define an individual or the borders of
consciousness the limits of
consciousness is still
uh very much at the center of my uh my
intellectual interpre enterprises so
this is something that i'm trying to
explore more so
and this is something that i'm thinking
about these days whether the
unit of scientific activity is
especially a region in the
popular a population of neurons in the
brain of a scientist or an individual
scientist or a group of scientists so
these are all very interesting topics
thank you very much
thanks
for the response
so
dean and then blue
shield i think what you've done is
you've hit on a really important point
and that is that
whenever we do isomorphism
we can sort of take an iso an isovis
stance i've read a book a long time ago
by uh the editor author was james
brockwell it was
it was called um
uh the visual world and memory and what
he said was is that
the way that we capture
uh can be one of two types the eyes of
this stance that sort of isomorphism
that we're outside and we're creating a
representation with frames
around them
or we can be spatially enveloped which
kind of ties in really conveniently with
the idea of being
either in the
cubbyhole that bob is in or alice is in
or anybody that's within spatially
enveloped
within
that sort of
entailed world where we're sort of now
the subject of whatever the walls are
limiting us from being able to see
and so
i don't think we walk away from the idea
that
we can make models we just have to be
able to ask on a moment especially to to
blues point how do we how do we make
something available as opposed to
keeping it
sort of cleaved off or or sectioned off
we have to kind of take the perspective
or the view of the person who's
enveloped
who doesn't necessarily have that
isovist
slash model ability to nest thing and
look at the world from their eyes which
is
okay it's not what you're seeing
necessarily in terms of what's on the
page it's how you're entering the room
with maybe not as much background and
not as much ability to step outside of
all of this information
and start juggling and so i think that
is one of the really key points to try
to remember here when we model
that just because i have a model
that i can take that eyes of his stance
doesn't mean i am able to also remember
what it was like to be the one
sort of
captured or enveloped by less
information but still trying to catch up
i think if we can hold both up at once
it's back to that minimum
two things at once don't be surprised if
do be surprised if
or active and inference like i think i
think what we're what we're really
basically saying here is
bumping it up by including two things
that sort of depth perception piece
yes it does make it more complicated or
complex but that doesn't mean it's
it's overwhelming it gets overwhelming
if you try to do i guess maybe seven or
ten dimensions at once but
we can bump up to two
we can take the eyes of his stance we
can do the model and we can also be
remember what it was like to be
spatially enveloped
you're gonna get overwhelmed and
surprised by the real world when the
train
comes at you if you don't have depth
perception so
it's a very interesting
take dean like
yes two and two is truer than one but
also there's other benefits too blue
so just to kind of clarify like what i
was talking about earlier and then add
on to what dave was saying like i i want
to know how to draw
a partial marsh markov blanket like how
do how do you like like to me a markov
blanket like represents a distinct
boundary between like self and other
internal and external and so how do you
make this kind of partial
markov blanket and i like what dave was
saying or about what um his teacher put
forward about
the conversation being
a unit of consciousness and i am very
much
a ascriber to pan psychism like i i
don't think that
it necessarily needs to be a
conversation between two humans um
but but really maybe fundamentally each
relationship between two objects perhaps
each relationship has then its own
markov blanket like you know my heart
and my
liver have a relationship with each
other that that itself is encapsulated
with a markov blanket and this can you
know be attributed to any two cells or
two organisms or
so on and so forth
uh
very well so by the way of uh an example
i completely agree so
uh
especially about the part that this uh
so uh
uh
well i do not want to
use
the term conversation because i do not
know the theoretical implications very
well but
uh i think that
so
uh
i used this when i started this project
for example on
modeling scientific activity as some
sort of active inference i was thinking
of individual scientists as
the units of
uh
scientific activity so science an
individual scientist has been enveloped
by markov blanket and she was trying to
get an access to the causal structure of
the world by forming influences from
beyond the
blanket but
as i worked more on this
aspect i understood that the situation
is becoming complex uh very quickly so
uh then i just uh then i thought that we
could put all of the scientific group or
scientific community inside the mark of
blanket and then try to explain their
relation with the environment as
uh the parts of a general markov blanket
by just expanding the scale that
includes them and then at the stage i
also told that we could also moder in
the same way that we could envelop the
relation between uh two scientists
inside the markov blanket we could just
expand that and also include the
artifact the object the major the
scientific
uh experimental tools inside the
community of the scientists so
scientific activity is basically about
the relation between scientists
scientists human human activity and
human artifact uh relationship and
scientific activities distributed
to
all of this group which includes both
human beings and
artifacts and then like depending on
your take on
uh free energy principle whether you are
defending a representation of this
stance or an activist stance you can
speak about the relation of this group
to their environment in terms of
classical representation
or
coupling or a hybrid view which includes
both representations and coupling
thank you very interesting makes me
think about science and technology and
how the word science relates to like a
lot of inference and
psi and scry and all that and then
technology technique
and that has a little bit more of the
implications of tool
deployment and finesse and measurement
and
the blurry line between science and
technology and the who and the what and
the how
so it's very cool
let's um in our last little bit here
first if anybody watching live has
questions we totally can
address them
but this was the question that we left
off on
at the end of the 0.1
video
which was
how do you utilize functional and
effective connectivity in active
inference analysis to better inform an
answer to a question
such as in football why i scored the
goal so how does that enrich in analysis
because we've talked a lot about how the
chosen
models deployed by scientists are goal
driven
and so what exactly is
active inference
helping us
do or how is it enriching our account
of a situation like scoring a goal
in a sports ball game
well
as a philosopher i feel that i have to
stay silent about this question to avoid
revealing my deep ignorance of the
technical aspects of how this works so
i i mean i have some general ideas and i
can try but i think that it would be
better to
stay silent and not reveal my ignorance
how about start it off with something
ignorant and then we'll see if any other
researchers have thoughts
well uh i do not know about this
specific example but for me the
distinction between functional
connectivity and effective connectivity
was about the
our causal physical aspects of the
target system and the general
global and structural features of the
system so i was not thinking of this in
terms of so
the point that i was trying to make
whether to try to focus on modeling the
causal physical aspects or focus on the
structure or global aspect would be a
matter of the interest of the scientists
or the modeler whether at the
moment or whether
in order to do the task at hand she
prefers to stay focused on the general
aspect speaking about the relation
between different parts in
unifying structural terms or going into
the details and trying to model
local specific
uh features
i'm not quite sure how i can apply that
to the
the example of
scoring a goal
dean
or anyone else
i just think it's in scoring the goal
again
pre pre-kicking the ball you could be
asking yourself two questions
why am i surprised
about the result or
should i be surprised about the result
because i think that's what active
inference
affords it gives you that
it gives you that possibility of
two outcomes i scored a goal or i kicked
it up into the stands but before you
actually kick the ball
perhaps
perhaps if you're not really really
skilled at kicking a ball
you can ask yourself whether or not
there's enough
enough in this particular case
mechanical familiarity and background to
actually finish off what you
intended to do
that's what i think active inference
allows for but again my ignorance shines
through too so
okay i'll
give a thought
so i think there's active inference and
then there's functional and effective
connectivity because
functional effective connectivity have
gone back further so first
applying the techniques of functional
effective connectivity help us separate
out hypotheses about physical causal
mechanisms
from
a whole variety of different kinds of
edges that might be
uh applied like there's time correlation
there's mutual information
there's um
change with respect to like you know
condition on this one going up in that
split second this one goes up as well so
all kinds of different
uh edges that can be drawn
essentially in a graphical
framework so not just like visual but on
a nodes and edges
active inference gives us a
i mean among other things so this of
course would not be a
complete or
authoritative answer but it does provide
us with a a framework and a nexus
and a community
that can scaffold and nurture
accounts of the target phenomena so
kicking a goal
we want to have the biomechanics
researcher
and the force on the knee and
physical rehab
and then also
there's an easy way to go into like the
um social inter-subjectivity of the game
rules and
regimes of attention and thinking
through other teammates
and um
[Music]
cyber physical systems of the soccer
stadium
and then like reviewer two just
addressing
the inner
or outer critic
and knowing that we don't need to to
have a theory of everything to talk
about
the ball being kicked
so i'd say that actin specifically
provides um
value for the researcher the the goal
scoring researcher
because it will help them reduce their
uncertainty about what contribution to
make to the research literature by just
saying like giving really good
connection points if they're doing the
biomechanics paper
it can have awesome connection points to
the cultural and the social and all of
that and if they're doing the social
paper it could have nice articulation
with
the biomechanics
and that would even be before we get
into the um
some of the details of the active
modeling per se um
so
if anyone in the live chat would like
any
final questions otherwise we will sort
of
cruise out
you know in the dot zero we do the
background and it's the time that we all
need to take to like work through these
very
provocative and interesting and
far-reaching papers then dot one is a
lot of times like a mess
because we're exploring a lot of
different avenues and we never finished
them all in the dot 2 but this is sort
of where we
take off into our next
set of discussions it happens to be that
in the coming weeks we're going to be
talking about the nature of
self representation so that might have
some themes but majeed i'm just curious
like what
are you excited about for 2022
what um
directions or policies
are like exciting to you now that you've
very recently completed this work
well uh uh i'm uh excited about a new
book that is under review and it's true
so
uh a structural realism as i said was
the
the officialism of philosophy of science
for quite a while
and
uh i tried to develop a cognitive
version of a structural realism before
no in a new book that is
in a new book that is going to be
published it is not i mean it is a
sequel to the book that you are seeing
in a new book that is under review right
now i'm going to play show the social
aspects of scientific activity so
a structural realist despite all of
their virtues they were not too much
attending speaking about the social
aspects of science and i think that that
aspect has has been to some extent
neglected in the contemporary philosophy
of science so it has it had its high day
in works of thomas kuhn and fireband and
then it has been pushed into the
background and now i'm
building up on free energy principle
so the theories of social communication
that are grounded in free energy
principle to bring back the
uh
uh this discourse on uh social aspects
of scientific activity so the book that
is under review is
the title is aptly called
uh bringing social awareness to a
structural realism so i'm very excited
about that i still do not know whether
it will pass the review and whether it
will go
to the press or not but i'm very much
excited about that
nice
um
reminds me of bruno latour reassembling
the social of course different aim
but that almost feels invoked in the
title well uh well it is a different aim
but as i say uh it has so it is mainly
about works of thomas kuhn and
fireman but it also has references to
the works of social constructivist la
tour and others and
specifically uh sorry i have to change
the place to put my laptop into the
charge again but uh the thing is that
uh
lotto was one of the main people who was
complaining about this kind of
uh dismissiveness of social aspects of
scientific activity and i think that
people who were working in distributed
cognition were trying to they're
actually explicitly mentioning works of
lottery and some other
social cognitives to
uh find
a foothold for bring for
creating cognition or knowledge as some
sort of distributed social activity
uh so uh what i try to do is to develop
some sort of
elective distributed account of uh
scientific cognition this has been
something that people such as ronald
geary have been doing before and no uh
non-synergy and some other people are
doing these things but what i was trying
to do is to
try to reinforce and reconstruct this uh
very interesting insights by drawing on
recent development in free energy
principle so some sort of free energy
principle account of social
communication i'm building upon that to
reconstruct uh classical accounts of
distributed scientific cognition which
as well has its roots in works of latter
and some other social cognition
social constructivists so you were very
sharp to spot the relation again cool
nice um
[Music]
connection there looking forward to that
like actor network theory
ant
distributed systems
kind of makes sense
um
well i think if anyone else wants to
give
a final
thought or comment anyone other than the
author then we'll provide the last word
to the author so blue and then either
dave or dean
this is a lot of like fun thought
experiments and um just thanks for your
time and
as any good paper opens more questions
than provides answers i think so
i'm curious to see what your next work
is and how it all unfolds in the future
thank you very much for for
your contribution as well
uh
dean and then dave if you would like
majida as as i mentioned earlier i hope
that uh
if if
in a couple months time and there's a
slot where you have some availability
i would like to also look at that um
[Music]
this work that you've done around
abduction and the idea of active
inference as well because i think
in terms of trying to be able to
cast a wider net and get a better sense
of how
we model and look at things through
through time frames both before during
and after i think that would be
something that
i'd like to take up because going
through this paper certainly
um
[Music]
brought a lot of things to the forum was
really really helpful so thank you very
much thank you for showing up today was
really appreciated
no so thank you very much for your
interest so i learned quite a lot too
both from participating today and from
watching the video the the previous
video of the discussions
great well yep as always super fun to
read and to interact with you to take it
from a
epistemic stigmargy
interaction with your asynchronous
artifact
into something that is spatially remote
but still
interactive hashtag effective
connectivity
um so
just keep in contact with us and anytime
you would like to discuss more or do
anything else with the lab just be in
touch and anyone else as well so
great times thank you everybody thank
you very much uh and sorry for being a
bit busy after teaching and
this end of the semester
hassle so thank you very much take care
excellent see you all later
you